<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Present condition of France in reference to her revenues comparing them with the infinite expenges [sic] she is forc'd to be at : demonstrating thereby that it is impossible for her to support her self if the war with the confederates continues / done out of French.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55694</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15266322</idno>
  <idno type="VID">103329</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240910939</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3238</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35378</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">15266322</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55694)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103329)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1192:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Present condition of France in reference to her revenues comparing them with the infinite expenges [sic] she is forc'd to be at : demonstrating thereby that it is impossible for her to support her self if the war with the confederates continues / done out of French.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Rhodes ... and John Harris ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Grand Alliance, War of the, 1689-1697.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103329:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103329:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Present Condition</hi> OF FRANCE, In reference to Her REVENUES, COMPARING Them with the Infinite EXPENCES She is forc'd to be at.</p>
            <p>Demonstrating thereby, That it is impossible for Her to support Her Self, if the War with the CONFEDE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RATES continues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Done out of French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Rhodes</hi> near <hi>Bride-lane</hi> in <hi>Fleet-street,</hi> and <hi>John Harris</hi> at the Harrow in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:103329:2"/>
            <p>Licensed,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>December</hi> 2d. 1691.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. Fraser.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Advertisement.</head>
            <p>THere is now in the Press, and will suddenly be publish'd <hi>The Triumph Royal:</hi> Wherein are describ'd the Triumphal Arches, Piramids, Pictures, Inscriptions, and Devices, to the Number of <hi>62.</hi> Erected at the <hi>Hague</hi> in Honour of <hi>William III.</hi> King of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> An Elaborate Piece of Curiosity, in <hi>62</hi> Figures: First done in <hi>Dutch,</hi> then into <hi>French,</hi> and now into <hi>English.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Henry Rhodes,</hi> and <hi>John Harris</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>THE Fourth Volume of Letters Writ by a Turkish-Spy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is in the Press, for <hi>Hen. Rhodes.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>
               <hi>MEdicina Practica.</hi> or, Practical Physick. Shewing the Method of Curing the most usual Diseases happening to <hi>Humane Bodies,</hi> &amp;c. With the Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>Praecipiolum,</hi> or Ʋniversal Medicine of <hi>Paracelsus.</hi> To which is Added, The Phylosophical Works of <hi>Hermes Trismegistus, Kalid Persicus, Geber Arabs, Artesius Longaevus, Nicholas Flammel, Roger Bachon,</hi> and <hi>George Ripley.</hi> All Translated out of the best <hi>Latin</hi> Editions, into <hi>English;</hi> and carefully Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and divided into Chapters and Sections, for the more pleasant Reading and easier vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing of those Authors. Together with a singular Comment upon the first Book of <hi>Hermes,</hi> the most Ancient of Philosophers. The whole Compleated in Three Books. By <hi>William Salmon,</hi> Professor of Physick. Printed for <hi>T. Howkins,</hi> in <hi>George-Yard</hi> in <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard-street, J. Taylor</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church Yard, and <hi>J. Harris</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> in the <hi>Poultry. 1692.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103329:2"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Present Condition</hi> OF FRANCE, In Reference to Her REVENUES, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THere are few Persons that suffer not their Eyes to be daz'ld at at the first Sight, with the great Power of <hi>France,</hi> and the appearing Riches of that Kingdom. The Repose, which one would think she enjoys within her self; her Progresses abroad, her Naval Strength, her prodigious Armies, and the great Number of Towns and Fortresses which she has won within her Enemies Countries, and upon their Frontiers, which render her own Provinces as it were inaccessible; all these things joyn'd together, are enough to deceive the Eye. But pry into her more narrowly, and you will find, that if on the one side this great Power appears invincible, and these immense Riches in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exhaustible, the first cannot support it self, but must inevitably sink under the Burthen of its own Weight; if the second, which is the Revenue, the principal Sinews of the other, and the main Spring that moves that mighty Fabrick, comes once to fail, or but to abate considerably, which has already come to pass. The People who supply'd these Revenues, but are now tumbl'd into ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most Misery, are an evident Proof of what we assert, altho' we wanted others much certain. But the Display which we are about
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103329:3"/> to make is without any Reply. Tis true, that a Crew of Anonymous Scriblers and others, by setting forth a prodigious Number of Pamphlets, have us'd their utmost Endeavours to make it out, that if the Grandeur of <hi>France:</hi> draws to a Period, she her self has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd her own Misfortune. They have set forth, with great care, the Violences which she has perpetrated both Abroad and at Home within <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er own P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ovinces, her Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ishings, her F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lshood, her Breac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Contracts, and Treaties; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Usurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Burnings, Sacriledges, her Persecutions and Extortions.</p>
            <p>They have prognosticated that all these Proceedings were as so many Avant Curriers and Occasions of her approaching Downfall. I must confess at the same time, that all this is not without good Grounds. For if we look upon the thing, in respect of Providence, it is impossible that Divine Vengeance should suffer a Domination so long to prosper, that has had no Regard to any Laws, either Divine or Humane, when the Contest was for Grandeur and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and many times committed many Mischiefs meerly to pleasure a haughty Fancy, when there was no Advantage to be reap'd by the Crime. If we consider her Conduct, in respect of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that are become her Enemies, it is impossible but all these law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less Actions must have provok'd 'em to that Degree, as never to hope for any Reconciliation. Her Allies may also judge by that, what they do expect from her, if once they should happen to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle her Anger, or if it should only come into her Head, that their Ruine might be serviceable to exalt her Grandeur. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>astly, it cannot be, but that even her own Subjects must be highly disgust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at her Government, in regard that though these Rigorous Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannies did not directly concern themselves, as it has many times happen'd upon several Occasions, yet it is always an unhappy thing to serve such violent Masters; as well for that the Hatred which Forreigners conceive against a Soveraign, rebounds upon the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as for that they ought to expect the same Usage, should it happen by Misfortune that the War should come home to their own Doors; and that he, to whom they yield Obedience, should be constrain'd to abandon their Defence. In a Word, I am perswad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that if the Confederates, for Example, should come to penetrate into the <hi>Dauphinate,</hi> the French would deal by that Province, as they did by the <hi>Pala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inate.</hi> So that those Writers that have made the Violences of <hi>France</hi> an Argument of her approaching Ruine, have not been altogether in the Wrong. But however it be, all these Reasons cannot pass for any other than Reasons of Plausibility,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:103329:3"/> not sufficient to satisfie and convince certain People, who being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed to more solid Arguments, submit to nothing but Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration.</p>
            <p>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>all therefore quit these sort of Reasons in this little Treatise, or if I make use of 'em, it shall only be as Accessories, upon which I shall not put any great Stress. My principal Aim is to shew, that by comparing the Revenues of <hi>France</hi> with her Expences, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining the Nature of these Revenues, we shall find that the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences vastly exceed the Income, I shall also shew by undeniable Proofs, that the Revenues of <hi>France</hi> are very much abated, and that it is impossible but they must fall every Day more and more. So that if the War continues, she must of necessity sink under the Weight, without any possibility of being able to support her self. But it is time to conclude this long Proem, least the impatient Reader cry out with <hi>Horace,</hi>
               <q>Quid dignum tanto feret hic promissor hiatu?</q> Let us come then to Matter of Fact. 'Tis certainly true, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the War which blazes now all over <hi>Europe,</hi> the Crown of <hi>France</hi> might reckon upon Rents and Revenues which were appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated and annexed to it, to the Value of about a hundred three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score and two Millions; besides Casualties, which formerly, and before the War in 1672. the French had mounted up to threescore Millions. 'Tis also as true, that since the Year 1685. that open Hostility was absolutely proclaim'd against all the Reformed in the Kingdom, the Rents have fallen near ten Millions, by reason of the Interruption and Disorder which it caus'd in Trade. Which was the reason that they began to grant considerable Indemnities to the Farmers, though they had taken the Farms at a fix'd and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Rent: and of this the Contradictory Decrees and Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that ensu'd, are Testimonies so notoriously publick, that they are no way to be call'd in question. 'Tis also certain, that the Reformed were they who had the principal and the greatest in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest in these Farms, considering their Trade both within and without the Kingdom. The Duties for Entrance, Passage, and carrying out of Merchandize which they pay'd, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to a vast Summ in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts of the Farms, Customs,<note n="(a)" place="margin">An Imposition of <hi>Trelupence Tournois,</hi> or the tenth part of an English Shilling upon all Goods Imported.</note>
               <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raines,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">An Imposition of the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth part of the Value of all Goods Imported and Exported.</note>
               <hi>Traittes Estrangeres,</hi> and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103329:4"/>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">The Books of Rates upon all Spiceries and Custom-house Gouds.</note>
               <hi>Tariffes.</hi> There are also some French Merchants in <hi>Holland,</hi> and in other Places, of which the Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Dealer pay'd before the Persecution above 25000 Livers (or 3125 <hi>l.</hi> Sterling) every Year in Duties to the King, and who the next three Years after that of 1685. never pay'd above 1500 Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vres a Years, which is not above 177 <hi>l.</hi> odd money. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was that the deceas'd Monsieur <hi>Colbert,</hi> who foresaw the Dammage that would accrue to the Crown by the Edict prohibiting the Reformed to be admitted into publick Offices and Management of the Kings Affairs, and lamented their being persecuted as they were every Day, could not forbear to oppose it with all his Might. But all his Remonstrances could not prevail against the Jesuitical Counsels and Resolutions which were then taken utterly to extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate the Reformed out of the Kingdom, whatever it cost.</p>
            <p>It is therefore evident, that before the Revocation of the Edict of <hi>Nantes,</hi> the Persecution had caus'd a considerable Abatement in the King's Farms.</p>
            <p>Now if we compare this Time with that which follow'd after, when several rich Merchants who still drove a considerable Trade, though much abated, were forc'd to fly the Kingdom, and carry'd along with 'em almost all their Effects, which was for the most part in ready Money, and settled their Manufactures and Traffick abroad; when several Families also, that rais'd the King's Duties by the Consumption of several Commodities, were likewise withdrawn, and that the Manufactures were almost utterly laid aside in all the Cities of the Kingdom, as well because they had not Vent, as for that the Workmen were hal'd away to the Wars; there is no doubt but all this caus'd a far more considerable Abatement in the King's Duties.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, the French make it their Business to spread it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, that the Farms of all the Grand Demesnes that were lett in the Years 1689. and 1690. receiv'd no Diminution by this present Conjuncture, and yet that the Price of 'em was rais'd too. But this is such a wonderful thing, that it may well be question'd, whether they who presum'd to divulge so idle a Story, had not a purpose to make themselves merry, by ridiculing the Prince, in whose Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour they forg'd a Fable so incredible. For from whence should such an Enhancement proceed? Could it be from the Increase of Trade? With whom should this mighty Traffick be? Certainly it must be with the People of the Antartick Regions, which the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:103329:4"/> Ships of the French had lately discover'd. For as for any Trade which they pretend to with the known Parts of the World, we see but little they have. But quite the contrary, excepting <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerland,</hi> a Country very improper to augment the King's Farms, and some parts of <hi>Italy,</hi> all other Commerce is forbidden 'em. But perhaps the preceding Farmers got too much, and the new ones are contented with a meaner Profit. But had it been so, we should infallibly have seen some Tax impos'd upon 'em. Besides, that though there is something to be gain'd, they are too sharp sighted in <hi>France</hi> to let the Farmers gain so considerably by the Bargains which they make.</p>
            <p>Then again, all <hi>France</hi> is sensible that the new Farmers are so far from acting independent in the Management of the Farms, that they only act as Overseers, for the better ordering and receiving of the King's Duties and Demesnes. The Labour which they take, and the Conduct which they observe in all the Places where the Kings Duties are demanded, evidently prove this to be a Truth. 'Tis well known that these Overseers had for their Expences, as also for their Advancing Money beforehand, and for their good Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, two Sous in a Livre, and were oblig'd to give an Account for no more then they receiv'd. Nor is this the first time that the Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers have been at this Lock. <hi>Le Gendre, Fauconet, Saunier, du Frenti, Bout,</hi> and some other General Farmers, before the Year 1689. though they had taken the Farms at a set Rate, were admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, at least they who desir'd it, to account for no more then they receiv'd, because it was clearly seen they had been Losers by the Abatements that had happen'd in their Farms, by reason of those Accidents and Casualties already mention'd. Others there are, who have only obtain'd considerable Abatements; which is so well known over all the Kingdom, that there are few People who know any thing of Business that can be ignorant of it. The Declarations and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees that have been publish'd upon these Occasions, and the great Failings of the principal Farmers, have been too publick, for any Body to deny what a ticklish Undertaking it is to meddle with those great Farms.</p>
            <p>Now if in time of Peace, and in the flourishing State of <hi>France,</hi> they were constrain d to allow the General Farmers considerable A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batements and Indemnities; what may be thought of it now, that the best Cities of the Kingdom are ruin'd, that the Nation is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of all forraign Trade, and that the King is forc'd to hurry his <hi>Militia's,</hi> his Bans, and <hi>Arrier-Bans,</hi> from Province to Province,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103329:5"/> and Frontier to Frontier, equally tiring out both Gentry and Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant, and exhausting all his Subjects with Marches and Counter-Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and lying up and down the Country remote from their Homes and Habitations. All this shews, that whatever Care is taken to publish the contrary, the Revenues of <hi>France</hi> amount not to above the half of what the Adorers of the Gallick Monarch would make the World believe. The particular Examination will make this out more clearly to be true.</p>
            <p>I shall begin with the Taxes Real and Personal, which the Crown levies over all the Extent of the Kingdom, excepting in some Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces which are govern'd by States. These Taxes were enhaunc'd before the War, 1672. and three Years after, to fifty one Millions a Year. But then the Poverty of the People, and the Interruption of Trade was such, that in the Year 1676. they were reduc'd to forty Millions; and in the Year 1678. to thirty Six Millions, and so they continued sometimes more, sometimes less, till the Year 1690.</p>
            <p>But in that Year it was, that the Receivers of the Taxes, having made it out, that it was impossible to collect 'em any longer accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that Rate, by reason of the Poverty of the People, and the Decay of Trade, the Desertions of the Protestants, and the Waste of the younger sort in the Wars, the Taxes were reduc'd to thirty Millions. Maugre this Abatement, in regard the same Inability still continu'd, there was a Decree of the Grand Council, by which all Cities, with their Dependencies, should in the Body of their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration be answerable for themselves, the Solvent for the Insolvent, to make good the Summ that was impos'd upon the Corporation, which put those that were taxable to unimaginable Confusions and Disorders, and contributes not a little to augment the Miseries of the People.</p>
            <p>The<note n="(a)" place="margin">The <hi>Taillon</hi> is a Tax that was rais'd by <hi>Henry</hi> II. <hi>An.</hi> 1549. toward the Increase of the Pay of the <hi>Gens d' Armes,</hi> that were Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letted in Towns and Villages, to enable 'em to pay for what they call d for, and prevent Disorders.</note>
               <hi>Taillon,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Subvention, is a Duty of the 20th penny, or one Sous in a Livre, laid upon all Merchandizes, to supply the Necessities of the State.</note> Subvention and<note n="(c)" place="margin">Subsistance, an Impost lay'd upon the People for the Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Soldiers in their Quarters.</note> Subsistance, which is receiv'd as a Tax by the extraordinary Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surers at War, before the War 1672 was enhaunc'd to three Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and five hundred thousand Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vres, since which time it has vary'd in rising and falling, till it fell to thirteen hundred thousand Livres, that is to say, till it fell to two Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, two hundred thousand Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vres.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:103329:5"/>
            <p>Before the War in 1672 there were great Variations in the Price of the General Farm of the Gabells, or Imposts upon Salt; but it never exceeded nine Millions, one hundred and thirty thousand Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vres. During the first War, it fell above six Millions; and at length the Farmers who desir'd greater Abatements, were admitted to account for what they receiv'd. After the Peace in 1678, this Farm could not be enhaunc'd again any higher then twenty seven Millions, two hundred thousand Livres, though the <hi>Gabells</hi> of the conquer'd Countries were compriz'd therein; and at another time it was let at twenty six Millions, with Conditions of Abatement in Case of War; which shews, that though the General <hi>Gabells</hi> had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderably augmented by the Addition of those of the Conquer'd Countries, by the Duties impos'd upon Tabacco, Tin, and by a Sous in a Livre impos'd upon dry'd, fresh, and salt Fish, in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of <hi>Normandy</hi> and <hi>Picardy,</hi> Nevertheless, there was an Abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of above three Millions, now if this happen'd during the preceding War, and in a time of Peace at home, may we not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what Persons of Credit and Fidelity write from all Parts, that in the present Condition of <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Gabells</hi> for the Year 1690. did not amount to above sixteen Millions. This Truth will be easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believ'd, if we do but never so little consider what has been said of the Heart of <hi>France;</hi> and when we call to mind that the Product of this Farm chiefly proceeds from the abundance of Trade. But in regard there are few People that understand what is meant by <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells,</hi> and what Duties they include, I thought it necessary to give a short Explication of the Word. Under the Name of General <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells,</hi> are comprehended the three Bishopricks of <hi>Metz, Toul</hi> and <hi>Verdun,</hi> the Demesnes and Salt-pits of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the Salt-pits and Demesnes of <hi>Franche Conte.</hi> They are the principal Product that swell the five great Farms, which consist in the Duties that are lay'd upon Merchandize, Provisions, Druggs and Spices, Imported and Exported out of the Kingdom. They are call'd the Five Great Farms, by reason of their being joyn'd to those of the same Nature in the Frontier Provinces, as <hi>Normandy, Picardy, Champaigne, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy</hi> and <hi>Lionnois,</hi> comprehending also the Provostship of <hi>Nantes,</hi> Convoy and Comptably of <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> Exportations from <hi>Charente,</hi> Customs of <hi>Lyon</hi> and <hi>Valence,</hi> Patent of <hi>Languedoc, Provence</hi> and <hi>Arzat,</hi> the Transportations from <hi>Rousillon,</hi> Duties of fifty Sous <hi>per</hi> Tun upon Fraights of Forraign Vessels, Duties upon Tabacco and Tin, and the Sous in every Livre upon Fish in the Provinces of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy</hi> and <hi>Picardy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:103329:6"/>
            <p>If there were any part of this Grand Demesne, of which the price ought to be fix'd, that would be Seignioral Demesne, and in Funds of Land, as Rents, Fines for Alienation under the Names of <hi>Lods</hi> and <hi>Ventes,</hi> of which the first are more chargeable than the second<note n="*" place="margin">The whole years profit of the Land, due to the Lord upon every Redemption, Collateral De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scent, or change of the Tennant.</note> Reliefs, Fifth Penny, and fifth part of the fifth Penny, Quit-rents, Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheats, Bastardies, together with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Duty and Redevances, or Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties annually payable to the Lord of the Fee, in Money, Corn, or Day-Labour, and annexed to Seigul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oral and Demesne Duties: besides all this, Houses, Castles, Culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated Lands, Mills, Meadows, Ponds, Woods, and other Estates, in the nature of Funds; nevertheless it has been known that these Demesnes before the Wars in 1672. have been taken by the Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers at 43 Millions: but during the first War, they suffered two Abatements, and were reduced to 36 Millions, 300 thousand Livres; but after that War, these Abatements fell so considerably, that no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy would take the Farm at a set Rent, without great Abatements, so that at present it is manag'd by persons under the name of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners, who for their Advances, their Pains and Expences, which are very great, have two Sous in a Livre; which is notoriously known in <hi>France:</hi> and what is more to be admir'd is this, That all these Demesnes have never been let higher, before the year 1663. then at three Millions, which makes many believe, that the excessive Rates to which they were afterwards rais'd, was the occasion of those Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittances, by vertue of which the Farmers sav'd themselves harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less.</p>
            <p>There are another kind of Duties which are call'd <hi>Aydes,</hi> which seem to be Fief-Rights, and almost of the same nature with those before-going; which nevertheless have suffer'd a very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable Diminution. But to make a better judgment of this, it will be requisite to enumerate the parts that comp se the Body of these Rights: these Duties therefore call'd Aydes, comprehend se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Impositions upon Wine, sold over the whole Kingdom, either by Whole-sale, or Re-tail, Brandies, Strong-waters, Cider, Beer, and other Drinks, Vinegar, the Entries of <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>Rouen;</hi> upon Wood to burn, and Timber, wrought and unwrought; Duties of<note n="(a)" place="margin">A Duty Collected at the Gates of some Cities, upon all Cattel that are driven in to be spent.</note>
               <hi>Pic Fourche,</hi> the Fief-Duty for the mark of Iron, the Duties of Nine Livres, Ten Sous <hi>per</hi> Tun, and a Sous, for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103329:6"/> every Pot of <hi>Picardy,</hi> and passage over the <hi>Som<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mposts and<note n="*" place="margin">An Impost upon Wine, of the twentieth, fourteenth and fifteenth <hi>Deneere,</hi> at the pleasure of the King.</note>
               <hi>Billio's</hi> of the Province of <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tagne;</hi> Duties upon Weights to the Duke of the said Province; the demesne Toll for the Stalls and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urateries of <hi>Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes:</hi> the one half of the Tolls and Assessments granted for Corporations of Towns and Cities to lay upon themselves: a third part of the Alienated Duties allow'd to certain Officers, except those of the Civil Government of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi> The Duties of Subvention and Subsistance in the Cities of <hi>Orleance, Rennes, Troyes, Diep, Caen, Chalons, Bourges, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vre de Grace, Amiens,</hi> and other Cities, as they are settl'd in the Book of Rates of the City of <hi>Alanson:</hi> the Duties of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Pied-Fourche</hi> of <hi>Rouen;</hi> five Sous upon every Bale of Wood, thirty Sous upon every Pack of Madder, four new Deneers upon every Bale of Merchandize carried into the Country: ten Sous and six D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neers for every hundred of white Linnen Cloth, as much for a hundred of Canvas; by the Duties that arise from the Privileg'd Assessments of the City of <hi>Rouen,</hi> by the doubling the mark in Gold; and lastly, by the Duty upon mark'd Paper and Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>All these Duties were let to Farm before the Year 1672. at 17 Millions 150 Thousand Livres: during this Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they suffer'd two diminutions, as appears by the Leases, of which the most Considerable amounted but to 4 Millions. After the Peace in 1678. they were Let at 18 Millions, and 18 hundred Thousand Livres, comprehending the Aydes of the New Conquests. 'Tis true, that in the year 1689. the Lease was made for no more than 14 Millions, but to be rais'd in case that things remain'd in the same posture, and that Peace continu'd; but in case of War and Loss, to give an account only for what was receiv'd. Now if we reflect upon the nature of these Imposts that maks up the Aydes, upon the present State of Affairs, and the diminutions which these Duties have suffered at several times, we must conclude, that they are now more considerably abated.</p>
            <p>Tis true, that the Crown has received every year since the Peace in 1678. ten Millions and something more for the Farms let at a certain Rate of the Demesne of the New Conquests of the Low Countries, besides what is contain'd in the general Farms already mentioned: these Demesnes lye in the Cities and Castellanies of <hi>Tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay, Douay, L'Ile, Cassel, Ypre, Balieul, Verni, Verneton, Paperingue,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103329:7"/> Loo,</hi> and their Dependencies; the City and Verge of <hi>Menin,</hi> St. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> and <hi>Aire, Valenciennes, Conde, Bouchain, Mauberge,</hi> and <hi>Bavet, Cambray, Cambresis,</hi> and all their Dependencies.</p>
            <p>After the Truce in 1684. all the Demesnes of the Country of <hi>Luxemburgh</hi> were augmented by the uniting of <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> and a great number of other Places and Countries, which the Royal Chamber of <hi>Metz,</hi> by an unjust Decree, without Example, adjudg'd to the Crown, under the name of Dependencies, encourag'd and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by the Violences of <hi>France,</hi> and by that means extended her Limits and Usurpations, I will not say beyond what the Treaties prescribe, but contrary to all manner of Treaties and Agreements. All which Countries joyn'd together, yielded a Revenue of about six Millions, and two hundred Thousand Livres; But since the War there have been considerable falls and abatements, being manag'd on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Intendants, that give an account for no more than they receive.</p>
            <p>It must be acknowledg'd that neither the Desertion of a great Number of Protestants, nor the present War, which has exhausted all the Provinces of the young and able People, and particularly those of <hi>Languedoc, Lyonnois, Provence,</hi> and the <hi>Dauphinate,</hi> nor the Misery with which the People are overwhelm'd, could hinder the General Farm of the Gabels of Salt from being still fix'd at 9 Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, and 100 thousand Livres, as well for that it is a Commodity which no body, tho' never so poor, can any more be without than without Bread, as for that they have rais'd the price to supply the abatement which the depopulation of the Kingdom has occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioned.</p>
            <p>Before the present War, it was look'd upon as good as certain, that the Sale of Offices amounted to five Millions every year, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Taxes upon Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and the Annual Duty, call'd<note n="*" place="margin">A Duty which the Officers of of Judicature and the Revenue pay to the King at the beginning of the year, to preserve their Offices to their Widows and Heirs in case of death, settl'd at the rate of the fiftieth penny of the value of the Office, in the year 1605.</note>
               <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> but within these two years that Revenue is become casual, and was rais'd one time to 18 Millions, by the great number of new Taxes that were laid upon all sorts of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and by the Creation of new Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and Masterships of Corporations, for which they were to supply the King with large Summs, by way o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Loan. But besides that, these are Funds which are not altogether inexhaustible, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are such as will suddenly be drain'd dry, since it is impossible
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103329:7"/> to create new Officers <hi>ad infinitum,</hi> and for that they who are Created, have not presently so much knowledge of their great Business, which is, to fill the King's Coffers; and this also shews the Poverty of the Kingdom: for though these Officers have the most ready money in the Kingdom, next to those that are interress'd in the Revenues, yet there are many of them that the King has been forc'd to acquit, either in part, or altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their new Taxes, as being convinc'd of their inability. Tis true, that to conceal their weakness in this particular, the King has pretended to discharge 'em for some good Services done him; but these are State Devices, which only delude those who know not such pretences have been made use of more then once, to hide the Infirmities of the Pocket. It is also true, that part of these new Offices which have been Erected, have been fill'd up; but tis as well known by what means it has been done: they apply'd themselves to those who are known to have Money by 'em; and they were told by the by, That it was better to lay out their Money in the Purchase of an Employment, which would bring in something every day, then constrain the King to lay a Tax upon their Heads: and the <hi>Financiers,</hi> who hate nothing so much as the word Taxing, had rather lay out their Money upon that bad Merchandize, then having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all: and yet notwithstanding all these Tricks, all the Offices are not fill'd up neither; another Argument of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The Tenths upon the Clergy of the Kingdom, amount eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry year to two Millions; and the Benevolences of the States of the Provinces of <hi>Languedoc, Provence, Burgundy</hi> and <hi>Bretagne,</hi> are well worth six Millions, and five hundred thousand Livres. 'Tis true they are given out to be much more worth in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Declarations; but every body knows that the King makes 'em Abatements afterwards, as it were out of Favour. All these Gifts have suffer'd no diminution during this War; and one would think they should have rather encreased, in regard the Clergy of the Provinces afore-mention'd, have given more freely than in the preceding years; and yet it is very cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that all these Revenues have not mounted higher than what we have already declar'd.</p>
            <p>'Tis also true, that they whose business it is to invent new ways
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103329:8"/> to get Money, have procur'd the King of <hi>France</hi> above fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Millions, by Fifth Pennies, and fifths of Fifth Pennies, Collation of Benefices, Mortmains, Estates and Possessions of all the Clergy, Eighth, and Tenth Pennies, by countenancing and Tolleration of the Goods of the Church Alienated, which has caus'd a strange confusion among the Clergy, as also among all private persons; in regard that to raise Money to preserve or regain 'em, both the one and the other find themselves al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most ruin'd: besides that, 'tis a Question whether the Law Suit, the Indemnities and the Protections, will not exceed the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal; so odious, troublesom and doubtful, is the verification of these Rights, there being very few Families in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom that are not entangl'd in these Affairs, and forc'd to pay these Duties; neither is any Ecclesiastical Person that has not a Temporal Estate exempted.</p>
            <p>I shall here make a short Digression, to shew after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner these Imposts are rais'd, upon the People, and the Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of those that live under such a Destructive Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>A little while after the Peace of <hi>Nimeghen,</hi> it was resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that payment should be made of the Eighth Penny, of all the Estates which the Corporations might have sold, and which were in the Hands of private Persons: the Pretence on the one side was, that the Corporations being Pupils, it was adjudg'd that they were always injur'd in the Contracts which they made, and who being also up to the Ears in Debt, were often constrain'd to sell their Lands dog cheap for ready Money: the Consequence which naturally flows from all this, supposing the truth of the Fact, is this, That the Eighth Penny which was demanded should be restor'd to the Corporations to repair their Losses: but nothing of all that, the King alone had the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of it, while the Corporations got not a Doit. But this was not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all; for the Supposition was false, in respect of se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eral Corporations that had sold their Lands at a very good rate, and the Purchasers thought they could have laid out their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney much better upon private Estates. Besides, there were some who having a good Quantity of Noble Mens Lands within <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir Jurisdiction, had purchas'd 'em to fell 'em again to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Peasants, who pay'd the Taxes that were upon 'em, to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103329:8"/> end the King's Money might be the more easily collected, there being a greater number of persons that were able to pay: but notwithstanding all this, no Lands were exempted from these Impositions, but the Eighth Penny was exacted with utmost rigour, not permitting private Persons to quit their Lands.</p>
            <p>Nor was this all, for sometimes the Corporations had sold Barren Grounds, which the labour and diligence of private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons had greatly improv'd; but for all that, they were forc'd to pay the Impost, not according to the price of the Sale, but the present value of the Land; or if by accident or otherwise the Land was gone to decay, then they never minded the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the Land, but the rate of the Purchase: besides that, there were a thousand false Expences for mark'd Paper, for the two Sons in a Livre, for the King's Receivers, for the Fees of Acquittances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> At first they were oblig'd to pay no more than the half down, giving time for the rest, which seem'd to be some advantage, but that was only to make the charge three times the more, for so many Payments requir'd so many new Acquittances, so much new mark'd Paper, so many other new Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences: after Acquittances in part, there must be Acquittances for the whole; then they must have a Discharge from the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Commissary, and another from the general Commissioner, and all ready Money. A Man would wonder how they could devise such ways to oppress the People; for certainly such a Series of raskally Knavery was never heard of before; and I am verily persuaded, that neither the King nor his Council knew any thing of it. In the search of the Publick Notaries, Registers for the Deeds of Purchase and Sale, at first they took no notice of any Summ that did not exceed a Crown, as thinking the eighth Penny not worth looking after; nevertheless, there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such Sales, as well for that formerly Money was more scarce than now it is, and consequently Lands were valu'd at a lower rate, as also for that the Corporations many times sold Lands that were of no value in themselves, but only they lay conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for particular Persons, who were willing to have an Estate entire within it self: the Commissioners therefore appointed for the recovery of the Eighth Penny, who very well knew what they did, neglected at first all those little Summs; but when they had once skimm'd the Pot, they return'd with a new charge,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103329:9"/> and under pretence that they had been losers by their Farm, or for some other reasons, which their Superiours either could not, or else had no mind to dive into, they obtain'd new Orders to pay in the Eighth Penny of all Lands alienated by the Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, at the price of a Crown, or under.</p>
            <p>The People were not much alarm'd at it at first, imagining that they might be discharg'd for ten, twenty, or thirty Sous at most; but they were deceiv'd, for the Expences of the Recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the Fees for mark'd Paper and Acquittances, amounted to four times more than the principal Money. I have heard seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Country-men tell the Commissioners, that they had no need of an Acquittance, that the Sum was not worth the trouble, and that they would relye upon their honesty, and that it was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough if they did but set it down Receiv'd in their Books: but the Commissioners would not receive their Money, if they would not take an Acquittance; and good reason, for that Acquittance came to ten times more than the Summ for which it was given. Some were so obstinate as not to receive it, but they paid sawce for their refusal; for they were made to pay four times more than the Principal came to: and thus were the poor People harrass'd by these Scoundrels of Collectors. Nor is the Cruelty much different in the Collecting the other Imposts, which it would have been much more to the purpose to have inserted into <hi>The Sighs of</hi> France, then the pretended Project proposed to the King's Council, to make himself Master of all the Estates of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as in <hi>Turky:</hi> a Project that was never in the Head of any person, but the Author of that Pamphlet; whereas there is nothing so true as what I have related; <hi>Cujus magna pars fui:</hi> that is to say, as being a Sufferer my self, not one that caus'd others to Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. But to return to our Subject.</p>
            <p>It must be acknowledg'd, That the Crown has gain'd above 18 hundred thousand Livres, by the new Infeoffments,<note n="*" place="margin">Which are Rights that the Lord of the Soil claims to the tenth, thirteenth, and fifteenth Sheaf, after the Harvest is reap'd.</note>
               <hi>d' Accrue,</hi> and <hi>Champaert,</hi> by the Re-union of several Sand-Hills, Islands, Eighths, and Penin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sula's in the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and several other Rivers in the Kingdom, which has cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed such a confusion among the Proprietors, and their Sureties, that their Indemnities and Charges have far exceeded that Summ.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103329:9"/> In which respect there has been most dreadful Injustice practis'd, which has reduc'd to Beggery Persons extreamly rich before. There is a Gentleman of <hi>Xantoigne,</hi> who shall be nameless, who could tell much more of this by woful experience. The Death of Monsieur <hi>Louvois</hi> has reunited the Postage of Letters to the Royal Demesne, which brings in fifteen hundred thousand Livres to the Crown. They have also found a way by Loans upon the Town-House of <hi>Paris,</hi> and the <hi>Tontin</hi> to scrape together about fifteen Millions, since this War began. But these are Debts for which the King is Security, the Interest of which consumes every Year five Millions out of the Duties of Entry and Gabells upon the Salt which is spent in <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is also to be added about two Millions, arising from the Sale of Wood, and the King's Rights in the Waters and Forrests over all the Kingdom, and Estates purchas'd or releas'd. And I leave out near six Millions arising from the <hi>American</hi> Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, in regard that Revenue is intermix'd with the General Great Farms; besides that, they are extreamly abated since the War. 'Tis well known that the Companies and Associations, in reference to the <hi>American</hi> Trade, of which the King is the Chief and Principal Head, are utterly exhausted, and reduc'd to make new Funds to keep up their Reputation; that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable Losses they have sustain'd, the Interruption of Trade, their Inability to supply the Charge of Fleets and Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and their being refus'd their Share of the Profits and Prizes that have been taken from the Enemy by the King's Ships, has altogether disabled 'em to support their Corporation. So that 'tis said, they have resolv'd to give up all into the King's Hands, to do as he pleases himself.</p>
            <p>The two last Years, the Clergy by way of Benevolence, for the Support of this War, contributed about eight Millions, which being added to their other Expences, of which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready spoken, has reduc'd a great part of that voluminous Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to the Order of Mendicants.</p>
            <p>Lastly, We may put to the same Account the Kings enhaunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Value of Money, and his Melting down, not only the Church Plate, but his Commanding into the Mint all the Court Cupboards of his Subjects, of what Degree or Quality soever; whereby the Crown has given a most evident Proof
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103329:10"/> of her Inability, which it behoves us carefully to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</p>
            <p>'Tis certainly true, that while Monsieur <hi>Colbert</hi> liv'd, there was a strict and frequent Enquiry made, what Money there was, either in Gold, Silver, or Copper, that might be currant in Trade <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver the whole Extent of the Kingdom; and it was found that before the War in 1672, it amounted to three hundred and sixty Millions of Livres; and though this be not a thing generally known, however there are very few of the more cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious sort, and the Officers of the Revenue, that are not well inform'd of it. During, and after that War, which ended in 1678, by the Treaty of <hi>Nimeghen,</hi> they were sensible of a Diminution of above forty Millions; and in all probability, one would have thought that this Diminution should have been supply'd by the New Conquests, and by the great Advantages of the Treaty of <hi>Nimeghen,</hi> and afterwards by the Truce of 1684, and by the Forrain Demesnes, of which the Crown had made her self Mistress by Force of Arms; yet quite the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it was observ'd, that the Money was lessen'd above twenty Millions. Which Diminution proceeded from the Violences of the Collectors of the Farms, too frequently exercised upon both Clergy and Laity; from the Rashness of those that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag'd the Affairs of the King, Clergy and People; from the outragious Persecution of the Protestants, who had a conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Share of the Wealth and Riches of the Kingdom in their Hands, and highly contributed both to the Increase of the Farms, and the Trade of the Nation, from the expensive Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications which were rais'd, as well in the Enemies Country, as upon the Frontiers, which carry'd vast Summs among the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the prodigious Prodigality that was exercis'd in the Courts of Forraign Princes, to corrupt their Favourites, and keep their Masters themselves in Pension. It is also requisite for confirmation of what we have said concerning this Diminution, to observe by the by, that of all the great Number of Merchants and Bankers that were in <hi>France</hi> within these twenty Years, the Richest have been forc'd to break, through that same most dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Oppression of the Publicans, wherein they were invelop'd together with the People.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:103329:10"/>
            <p>As for the Merchants and Bankers that still bear up, some of 'em dealt for a hundred thousand Crowns a Year, that for some Years since would have thought themselves happy to have dealt for ten thousand. And now behold another Proof of our Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact, so clear and convincing, that it is not in the power of the most passionate Votaries to the Crown, to make any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to it; which is this, that the King having order'd all the Money in the Kingdom, as well Gold and Silver as Brass, to be carry'd into his Mints, to be there new stamp'd, paying the Augmentation ordain'd, which is almost a twelfth part: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless, hitherto, notwithstanding all the Decrees and Edicts that have been set forth and proclaim'd, notwithstanding all the Penalties denounc'd, and all the Diligence it has cost 'em, there has not been carry'd into the Mint, together with that which the King himself sent in, above 65 Millions, of which there is no question to be made, in regard the Augmentation of the King's Duties for the Coinage hardly amounted to six Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions and five hundred thousand Livres. Which is so notoriously known in <hi>France,</hi> that not one of the Officers of the Mint can deny it, especially in the Cities where the Changes have been made, but also they that never concern themselves in Business.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, that all the Pieces of Plate and Money that are in the Kingdom are not brought in Evidence. For in regard that the People are sensible of the Necessities of the Crown, and are justly afraid least the King should seize upon all the rest, they have taken care to hide their Talent as safe as they can, choos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather that it should lye useless, and so suffer a kind of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digency themselves, then to appear full of Money and great Merchants, by living splendidly, which does not a little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the Ruine of all Trade. Nevertheless, all that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Persons may have conceal'd, cannot supply the Defect of so many Millions of coyn'd Money as are found wanting to what has been in the Kingdom. The reason is, because the People not being very rich, were forc'd to bring to light more Pieces than they would have done to supply their present Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities, though they durst not make use of 'em till they had carry'd 'em to the Mint.</p>
            <p>We are also farther to observe, that the Advantage which seems to redound from the new Coinage of the Money, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>verting
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103329:11"/> into Coin'd Pieces such a considerable Quantity of Church and House Plate is not so considerable as it seems to be at first. For if on the one side, the price of Money be advanc'd, on the other hand, all Commodities, Provisions and Merchandizes are very much risen; so that the King himself, considering how many sorts of Merchandizes and other Commodities he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain'd to buy for the Supply of his Forces both by Sea and Land, consumes within a very little, all the Advantage he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives by the Change. More than this, we must consider, that only his own People suffer all the Loss, in regard this Aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of his Pieces is cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant no farther then within the Extent of his own Dominions, and not in Forrain Countries, where the new French Money is not receiv'd but at the old Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue. We are also farther to observe, that at the same time that the Value of his Pieces was rais'd in <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Louidore</hi>'s fell in <hi>Holland;</hi> and whereas that in the Year 1686, they went at nine <hi>Florins</hi> fourteen <hi>Sous,</hi> after the Augmentation, they were worth no more than nine <hi>Florins,</hi> eight, and sometimes nine <hi>Sous.</hi> So that at the bottom, whatever Augmentation they make in the Money, it will never be able to equal nor come near that Plenty, as there was among the People before the present War. Nay, tho' they should melt down all the Gold and Silver that remains in <hi>France,</hi> and may be found out, 'tis much to be question'd, whether it would come near that great Abundance that was in the Kingdom before the Year 1672, because that both Ecclesiasticks and Seculars use all their Arts to hide what they can, for fear of being afterw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rds depriv'd of it by some un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected Tax, or by some new Squabble of the Collectors.</p>
            <p>By all this Display, 'Tis evident that all the Revenues of the Crown are casual, or proceed from the strength of Trade, or the Sweat of the People. And thus it was seen, that in the Year 1683, the Gabells, the Five Great Farms, and Duties thereto belonging, the Aids, Entries, and Rights thereto ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining; all the Demesnes of <hi>France,</hi> and of the conquer'd Countries, with the Duties thereto annexed, were set at a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Millions, six hundred sixty seven thousand Livres, with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves of Conditions in Counter Deeds; I say, with Reserves of Conditions, since it is certain that the Farms were under akind of Disguise, by reason of the Augmentation of a third part.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103329:11"/> For the whole was afterwards reduc'd to great Abatements, or else the Farmers were allow'd to account for no more then they receiv'd. In the same Year 1683, the other Revenues, <hi>viz.</hi> the Taxes and <hi>Taillons</hi> were lett at 38 Millions, the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells of the Salt of <hi>Languedoc, Lyonnois, Provence,</hi> and the <hi>Dauphinate</hi> at nine Millions; the Benevolences of the Clergy and Provinces at eight Millions; the Casualties of Offices and the <hi>Paulete</hi> at five Millions; the Sales of Wood, and Duties thereupon, at eighteen hundred thousand Livres. All which amounts to an hundred si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y two Millions, six hundred sixty se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thousand Livres. After this Farm was out, and in the Year 1687, the whole was lett at a hundred fifty four Millions, and four hundred thousand Livres; and at present, though all these Revenues were not abated above one Third, for the Reasons, and according to the Proofs already given, the 61 Millions, three hundred thousand Livres, or thereabouts, which the Court has receiv'd these three last Years, by the violent Extortions of the Collectors, and Casualties already mention'd, would not suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice by much to supply the Abatements and Diminutions before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd. But to make these Truths out yet more plainly, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves us to give a general Idea of the Condition of <hi>France,</hi> which, as strong as it appears to be, requires a stronger Imagination to believe the Reality of it.</p>
            <p>They who are never so little vers'd in the Knowledge of Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the Intreagues of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> may have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd, that toward the end of the Reign of the <hi>Valois,</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues of the Crown, with much ado, amounted to sixteen Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions a Year. <hi>Henry</hi> the IV. rais'd 'em to thirty Millions: Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Richlieu,</hi> under the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. advanc'd 'em to fifteen Millions more; and after him, Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanc'd 'em to sixty Millions. The People of <hi>France</hi> at that time look'd upon this Augmentation as a destructive Oppression that would ruine 'em in a short time. This was that, which encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged the Zeal of the Advocate General <hi>Talon</hi> to make several Harangues, that are in Print, to the King, in the Years 1649, and 1650. Wherein he lay'd before him, with much Eloquence, the miserable Condition of his People, by that same Throng of Impositions. He compares 'em to Beasts, for that they had nothing but Oates for their Bread, and Water for their Drink.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103329:12"/> After the Decease of <hi>Mazarine, Colbert</hi> being advanc'd to be Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-intendant of the Finances, under the Title of Controller General, put in practice all the Projects which that great Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster had left him. He began to settle the most admirable Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the Civil Government, and in the Management of the King's, and the Publick Revenues. He enlarg'd the Trade of the Nation with a great Company of Manufactures, set up Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies and Associations for the <hi>Indies</hi> and other Forraign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and in a word, neglected nothing which he thought might be for the Benefit of the French Monarch or Monarchy. While things were in this Condition, his Brains and Hands were always at work to nip the Coffers and Purses of the People, without any regard either to Quality or Condition, so he might cram his Master's Treasury, and second his ambitious Desires. And it may be truly said, that he it was who contributed the most to the present Grandeur of <hi>France.</hi> And he it was that rais'd the Revenues of the Crown to an hundred sixty two Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, by the Addition of the greatest Part of those Duties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned, unheard of before, for so many Ages together, under the Reigns of the preceding Princes. Nor did he stop there; the Advisers and Inventers of Impositions were receiv'd by him with all the Favour Imaginable; nor did they fail of Rewards. The first Objects of his Covetousness were the Persons who had handl'd the Publick Money, the Farmers out of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, that had been fingring the Money of the Clergy, the Publick, the Hospitals, and Commanderies. Upon them he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd round Taxes, which he made 'em pay by Force, and by the Exercise of a Thousand Violences. After that, Decrees upon Decrees flew abroad in Shoals, to establish the Duties and Impositions above specify'd: Besides which, behold a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of many others, which tho' seemingly not so heavy, yet were so great a Burthen to all particular Persons that were sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to 'em, that it has been hitherto impossible to give 'em any Ease. All Strangers residing in the Kingdom were tax'd, as well as they who had been ennobl'd an Age ago; and all they, who since that time had taken upon 'em the Quality of Nobles and Esquires, without any lawful Title verify'd in Form, they or their Issue were fin'd, and there were few Families, which by that Means were not drain'd of their Money. Taxes upon all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103329:12"/> new Infeoffments since forty years. Taxes of the eighth Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies upon all sorts of immediate Land Lords and Purchases; which is the Eighth Penny of the Principal of Quit-Rents and Annuities: Taxes upon Frank Feifs, Free Tenures, Base Feifs, and the Eighth Penny upon all Estates alienated by Religious or Lay Communities. Taxes and Fines for Crimes committed se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral years before: Taxes upon Woods, Forests, Parks, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens, Ponds, and other Royal Demesnes. Restitution, with the Profits for so long, of Usurpations made of such Estates and all other Domains, Eighths, Islands, Peninsula's, Rocks, Sand Hills, Tolls, Bridge Money, Ferry-Money, Gate-money, and Cross Toll. Cancelling of all new Leases, if the Deeds were not drawn according to the Declarations, which occasion'd great Losses and much Disorder, there being hardly any Deed that was not declar'd defective; in pursuance of which, the Propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties were adjudg'd to the King, and the Possessors condemn'd in oppressive Restitutions of the Profits. A new Establishment of the Right of <hi>Champart</hi> upon all manner of Possessions. A Tax upon Usurpations of Seignioral, Rights and Jurisdictions; and for the receiving Warranties and Surveys Legitimated to that effect. Taxes upon Pigeon Houses, and Livery-Horses, Horse-litters, Coaches, and other Carriages. Taxes upon the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Offices, and Augmentation of Wages, and the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Suppression both of the one and the other; to the end the Aspirers provided and dispossessed, might not laugh at one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. A Tax upon new Grants to the Bodies of Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Masterships in all Arts and Sciences, not exceping the Church-Wardens and Bearers of the Dead; nor exempting Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives for their Laying of Women, Sergeants, Cryers, Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peters, Sequestrators, and Commissaries of Distresses and Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Executions: upon Pawns which Creditors take of their Debtors till they have pay'd; and upon the publick Wardens of every Village-Community. A Tax upon all publick Nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Proctors, Registers, Ushers; and for a new creation of a Notary Apostolick. A Tax upon Registring of Christnings, Marriages, and Mortuaries. The re-prying into, and Adjudging forfeit, all Rights which are call'd Hereditary, and Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Mortgages, looking backward for the space of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty years, of which the Summs for which they were
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103329:13"/> engag'd had been swallow'd up by means of the Rents receiv'd exceeding Principal and Interest. The Re-Examination, and Adjudication of all Debts and Forbearances undetermin'd of all Accounts, as well Royal, as of the Clergy and Lay Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. A Tax of the eighth Denier, upon all Goods, Immovea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, alienated by exchange, Decrees and Sales. The Re-exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and violent Seizure of Goods that had belong'd to the Commanderies of St. <hi>Lazarus</hi> and <hi>Mount Carmel,</hi> with Restitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Profits. In a word, it might be said without any Aggravation, that the Advisers and Inventers of Taxes and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions could devise no way to get Money, but it was greedily embrac'd, and presently put in practice; so that it has been fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently seen that these Casualties have brought into the King's Coffers immense Summs; and some years above sixty Millions of Livres, not reckoning in the Tolls and Imposts setled in the Cities of <hi>Paris, Lyon,</hi> and other principal Cities. But all this while the People are so dreadfully overwhelm'd with these Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions, and by the large Summs of Money which all the Cities have been constrain'd to give to the King, that at present they are absolutely drain'd, and hardly in a Condition to subsist, especially now that Trade is almost ruin'd. So that having lost the Use of Money, they are forc'd to revive the Primitive Times, when all the Trade among Men confisted only in the Barter of one Commodity for another.</p>
            <p>It is convenient also, that you may be the more sensible, how these People are oppress'd to observe that the Collecting and clearing the Accounts of all these Taxes aforemention'd, costs almost as much as comes into the King's Coffers. Besides that, the Commissioners employ'd for the Recovery of these Summs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falk almost a third part for their Pains and Trouble. So that we may say that instead of a hundred sixty two Millions they should receive two hundred and fourteen to give the King his Due, considering the infinite Swarms of these Vermine that pester the Countrey.</p>
            <p>Nor is it only by these Extortions that we may discover the overwhelming Poverty of the People of <hi>France,</hi> there is yet another Proof that seems to be beyond all that has been said, and that is this.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:103329:13"/>
            <p>'Tis a Truth acknowledg'd by all those that understand the Fertility of <hi>France,</hi> That in regard this Fertility is not very great in Corn, it is impossible there should be enough for the Subsistance of the People; and if Corn were not frequently Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported from forraign Countries, the dearness of Provision would produce considerable Calamities. In a Word, those persons that have been employ'd in the Sea-port Towns, to Collect the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Importation and Exportation, have observ'd, that for one Load of Corn carried out of the Kingdom, there is import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed four; and in regard the present War deprives the Kingdom of that Plenty, and that Trade, so we see by sad Experience the Loss which it causes; seeing that during the good and plentiful Harvests, in the year 1689, and 1690. 'tis well known, that a Load of Wheat weighing 360 pound, was sold for ten Livres, and a Load of Oats, containing 64 <hi>Picotins</hi> (which are five pints of our Measure) for five Livres: nevertheless, because that in the year 1691. there was a general Drowth for some Months, attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with some Blastings and Smuttings of the Corn, in most of the Provinces, we may truly say, that the Seed was hardly dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, which enhaunc'd the price of Wheat to five and twenty Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vres a Load, and that of Oates to ten Livres; from whence it may be justly fear'd, that the price of both will still rife, more especially since Chesnuts, of which there wont to be great plenty, have fail'd above one half of what they us'd to be. But then again, here is another thing that has extreamly augmented the Misery of the People, which is, That the Vines in most part of the Provinces were kill'd by the Rigour of the fore-going Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the white Frosts that fell in <hi>May</hi> last, so that Wine is sold at five Sous a Pint, which formerly was not worth above one Sous a Pint, which makes out on the one side, what I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd, That the Fertility of the Soil of <hi>France</hi> is hardly suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to support the People: and if it come to fail never so lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, they are exposed to great Hardships. On the other side, it must be acknowledg'd, That the Prohibition of Trade continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it is impossible that <hi>France</hi> should avoid a general Disorder and Misery; and in regard that Money grows scarcer every day than other, and for that the poor People are ignorant what that sort of Metal is, there is all the probability in the World, as we are assur'd from several parts, that a vast Quantity of Land must
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103329:14"/> lie untill'd; to which if we add, the destructive Extortions which the People suffer, through the Violence of the Maltoting Cater-Pillars, it is demonstrable, That 'tis not without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son the Court of <hi>France</hi> is afraid of the dangerous Consequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, threatned by the Despair of a provok'd People, and that for the preventing of 'em, they keep such strong Garisons in all the Provinces: they who have Travell'd all the Provinces, have observed, and may now more sensibly observe, That there are a very great number of persons, who have no other for their daily Nourishment than Bread made of black Millet and Acorns, with which they formerly were wont to fat their Hogs and other Beasts.</p>
            <p>Then again, consider the loss which the Parisians in particular, and the French in general, suffer, of the Money which a great number of Forraigners brought in and spent in the Kingdom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the War, which amounted to above ten Millions of Livres, and which it will be no difficult thing to believe, if we but call to mind the vast number of Strangers that resorted thither; which on the one side brought in Forraign Money, and on the other side occasion'd a considerable vent of Provisions and Merchandize, and kept up a Forraign Trade, all which has ceas'd since the War.</p>
            <p>Lastly, let us but examine the Condition of the Nobility and Gentry of the Kingdom, from the highest to the lowest, and we shall find them generally labouring under the severe Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Want and Poverty. How many are there, whose low con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition disables them from serving in the Arrier-Ban? and they that did so, left behind 'em evident marks of that Misery which is their daily Companion, tho' the King allow'd them half Pay. Formerly the Nobility were as remarkable over all <hi>Europe,</hi> for their Pomp and Expences, as they are now for their Poverty, and for their woful and cruel manner of living. There are hardly to be found at present fifty Heads of Families, that enjoy a Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of fifty thousand Livres of Annual Rent, the rest are main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by their Employments, or Favours of the King, or by the means of Ecclesiastical Benefices and Pensions, which the King fixes upon those Benefices by vertue of his Prerogative of Collation; or lastly, by the Commandaries of St. <hi>Lazarus</hi> and Hos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitals. The great Taxes and Re-examination of their Titles, which
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103329:14"/> the Nobility are forc'd to undergo, together with the great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonal Taxes which their Tennants Annually pay, and which consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably lessen their Revenue; and their willfullness to distinguish themselves by the Purchases of Military, Judicial, and Politick Employments, has not a little contributed to their Beggery.</p>
            <p>This puts me in mind of a Passage that happen'd in the Year 1668. at <hi>Montpellier,</hi> upon the Verification of the Nobility. The Intendant of <hi>Bezons,</hi> finding himself environ'd one day by a great number of Gentlemen, and perceiving coming towards him a Gentleman that made Glass, with his Habit and Cloak torn and patch'd, he went forward to meet him, receiv'd his Sack, and reading in the Ticket without side what it meant, he took him by the hand, and looking upon the Company, <hi>'Tis but reasonable Sir,</hi> said he, <hi>that I should dispatch you in the first place, I know your Worth;</hi> and then turning to the Company, <hi>Look you here,</hi> said he, clapping the Glass-maker upon the Shoulder, <hi>Here's a true Gentleman, he is as the King would have him to be.</hi> The truth of the Intendant's words is now found to be verifi'd, seeing the King has reduc'd almost all the Gentle men of the Kingdom to work for their Livings, like the Glass-Maker, and to fare hard.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matchiavil</hi> set up a Maxim, that was carry'd into <hi>France,</hi> by Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> and practised there by him and his Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors in the Ministry, <hi>That the People ought to be kept low, and that 'tis sufficient that they can but only live, because the Soveraign thereby has 'em the better at Command, and in a case of Necessity may have what Men he pleases, with a power to gratifie and raise 'em to Honours and Dignities according to their Deserts, by which means he strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens himself with the whole Force of his Kingdom, and becomes a Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to those that have the Misfortune to be his Neighbours.</hi> I know not whether this Maxim be true, but this I know, That 'tis not to be practised in <hi>France,</hi> and that 'tis absolutely impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble but that the whole Monorchy must sink at last, if that Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im be much longer made use of: that is a Maxim only for Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to follow who have prodigious Riches of their own, vast set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Demesnes, and not for a French Monarch, whose Riches and Demesnes only consist in the Sweat, Labour, Trade, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of his Subjects: Now if the means to exercise this Sweat, this Labour, this Trade and Commerce fail, as they do at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103329:15"/> inevitably the Strength and Authority of the Crown must sink under the Burthen; not to say any more.</p>
            <p>Let us go on to other Proofs, to the end we may quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn this <hi>Machiavilian</hi> Maxim, and at the same time come to the Conclusion of our Design. We must acknowledge, That if all these vast Revenues suffer'd no other Diminutions then what we have already observ'd, there might be some reason to believe that the Crown might support her self after a fashion for some time longer: but if we penetrate a little farther into the prodigious Expences which the Necessity of the Times, and the Disorder of Affairs, constrains the King to be at, we shall find, That the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences alone, not only swallow up these Revenues, these Casual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and these Loans, but also consume, by way of Anticipation, the best part of these Revenues and Casualties, if it be so that they can be obtain'd for the future.</p>
            <p>Let us look back a little, as far as the War in 1672. and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Riches and immense Summs that were scrap'd together, before it began, as well by the Annual Revenues, as by Casualti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and we shall find by the Accounts of the ten years, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded the year 1675. that they were Farm'd out at 150 Millions; but the Expences of that War consum'd the whole, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain'd the Crown to Contract great Debts upon the Town-House of <hi>Paris,</hi> and upon several Members of the Demesnes: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides which, we have found that since that War, the Crown has always receiv'd and spent half a Years Rent before-hand, of all the Farms; which continuing so till the year 1689. it cannot be otherwise, but that both the Annual and Casual Revenues, which have been since receiv'd, must be utterly consum'd, in maintaining such numerous Armies and Fleets, in the supply of such extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Assistances as he is forc'd to give, and in defraying the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and particular Charges, which has caus'd the King to make so many Retrenchments, even to the Regulation of the Dauphin's Court and Equipage, from whence, as well as from his own Court, he has banish'd all the General and Particular Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumeraries, and all that Profusion, that Magnificence, and that Liberality, which is so natural to the French: they have all been regulated in their Houshold Expence, and their Services of Plate; which plainly denotes that weakness of Purse, which we have observ'd, and the necessity which compels to a niggardly Frugality.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:103329:15"/> We are also to observe the vast Expences which <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. is forced to be at in all the Courts of <hi>Europe,</hi> not excepting the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Republick, in Ambassadors, Envoys, Agents, Pensioners and Spies; there not being few Courts, or Cities in Christendom of any Note, wherein he has not a great number of those sort of People; especially in those Courts, Republicks and Cities, which are his Enemies: nor does he maintain 'em only abroad but at home, observing the Maxim of Cardinal <hi>Richlieu.</hi> At <hi>Paris</hi> for Example, there is hardly any Cabarret or other publick Place, where they are not listning; and so it is in other Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and particular Places of the Kingdom. Now since they swarm so numerously within the Kingdom, where one would think there were no need of 'em, we may well believe what is reported from all parts, that abroad they exceed the Locust of <hi>Egypt</hi> in number, which is no small charge to the most Christian King. Then again, the vast Assistances that <hi>France</hi> affords to many Princes, if we may believe the voice of publick Fame; to some, for their Encouragement to continue War with his Enemies; to others, to oblige 'em to Neutrality; or else to keep their Neighbours in breath: all which are profusions of the Revenue, beyond imagination. 'Tis also known what vast Pensions he is oblig'd to give to his Confederates, to King <hi>James</hi> and all his Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, to the English and Irish Refugees in <hi>France:</hi> I have said it, and I say it again, that the Summs are prodigious which the King pays for the Rents setled at the 16th or 18th pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny upon the Town-House of <hi>Paris,</hi> for the <hi>Tontin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and to a great number of particular persons; in Wages, Pensions, and Pay, an infinite number of Governours; General and Inferior Officers, both by Sea and Land; Officers of Judicature and the Civil Policy; and Officers of the Court, through the whole Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Kingdom. I refer the Reader to St. <hi>Martha</hi>'s Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, which, though it be defective, yet seems to exceed won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it self. At what a charge has the King been, and still con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues to be, for the raising and preserving the Lines upon the Frontiers, the Fortresses and Places in the Center of the Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, upon the Coasts, and within the Territories of the Enemy: What a number of Magazines are they obliged to fill with Corn, Bavins, Hay, Straw, Oats, Furniture for the Train, and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103329:16"/> Ammunition. The Charges of all these things is not to be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd, and occasions the draining the Provinces, of all their Provisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which has not a little augmented the scarcity and dearness of 'em. 'Tis known that <hi>France</hi> abounds not in Horses, more especially such as are proper for the Cavalry, and the Draughts of the Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, which constrains the French to purchase 'em at dear Rates, in Forraign Countries: and if they had been so exact as they should have been both in <hi>Germany</hi> and other Countries in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stillity with <hi>France,</hi> to hinder the carrying out of Horses, <hi>France</hi> could never have been so strong in Cavalry, as she is at present. What a vast Charge are they at for the numberless Recruits that they are forc'd to Levy? what Disorders have they produc'd in the Kingdom? what Violences have they not been forc'd to make use of to get Seamen? every Creature that look'd like a Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man upon the Coasts, or upon the Rivers, was hurry'd on Ship-Board. This affords us an occasion to observe an extraordinary defect in the <hi>Finances,</hi> in that the King has ordered all the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations in the Kingdom, to supply him at their own Charges with forty Thousand of the Militia for Recruits, which was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver done, unless the Crown paid for 'em. No Person will question but that the keeping of <hi>Pignerol</hi> and <hi>Casal,</hi> or an Army of thirty Thousand Men in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> amounts to more than six of the greatest Garrisons in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and an Army of 80 Thousand Men in those Countries, for that there is great plenty there, and Carriages easie; but in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> they must have Muses to carry all their Ammunition and Provision. To which purpose <hi>France</hi> has been forc'd for these two years to keep at least two Thousand five hundred of those Creatures, besides the Hire of an infinite number of other Beasts. 'Tis known that for one Journey from <hi>Grenoble</hi> or <hi>Antiles</hi> in <hi>Provence,</hi> to <hi>Pignerol,</hi> they gave for each Mule eight and twenty Livres.</p>
            <p>Nor is this the only Charge they are oblig'd to be at; for there is one greater still, which is the purchase of Provisions. For in regard that every thing is wanting at <hi>Pignerol,</hi> and for that <hi>Provence</hi> and the <hi>Dauphinate</hi> are not able to furnish 'em with Corn and Wine sufficient, having scarce enough for themselves, they were forc'd all the last Year to send for Corn to <hi>Antibes,</hi> a Sea Town, at ten Livres a Load, which being deliver'd at <hi>Pignerol,</hi> came to eight and thirty at least; Oates, at five
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:103329:16"/> Livres the sixty Picotins, or Pecks, which being deliver'd at <hi>Pignerol,</hi> came to eighteen Livres ten Sons; and now that the price of Wheat is rais'd both at <hi>Antibes,</hi> and all other Places from whence they fetch it, to five and twenty Livres a Load, and Oates to ten Livres, the Charge must of necessity be much greater, since that from <hi>Lyon,</hi> and the Banks of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> which is the Granary of those Parts, and of the Frontiers of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> 'tis impossible that the Travail of one Beast of Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age can cost less than thirty six Livres. As for Wine, 'tis known that the Mountains of the <hi>Dauphinate</hi> produce but very little, no more than of any other things necessary for the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of Humane Life, except Pasturage; and withall, that the Wine will not keep without a world of Trouble and Hazard; the People being forc'd to carry it upon Beasts of Burthen in Goat Skins, and to fetch it from the Banks of <hi>Rhosne,</hi> where it is already very dear, and the Carriage no less chargeable. By which it may be easily guess'd what a prodigious Expence <hi>France</hi> is at for the keeping of <hi>Pignerol</hi> and <hi>Casal,</hi> and an Army in <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edmont,</hi> in the <hi>Dauphinate</hi> and <hi>Provence.</hi> In short, this last Province is no richer than the <hi>Dauphinate,</hi> though it have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Ports upon the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> in regard both the People and their Trade are utterly ruin'd: and if it has contributed eight hundred thousand Livres as a Gratuity, 'twas an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Effort; as may be observ'd by the Trouble they had to raise the Money. Nor must I forget to add that many times these Carriages fall into the Hands of the <hi>Vaudois,</hi> and other Mountaneers, who make considerable Prize of 'em. Now if we consider all the Expences which I have enumerated, and several others which might be added; and observe withal, that all the Revenues and Casualties before-mention'd, are spent and gone, it will be a hard thing to believe that all the Toll-Gatherers, Extortioners and Hang-men they can employ will be able to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply all the Expences, and by consequence, that all the New Springs are drain'd up, and that unless they can work Miracles, and lay an Impost upon Pissing, as <hi>Vespasian</hi> formerly did upon Urine, it will be impossible for <hi>France</hi> to support it self long; and we may be assur'd that her Sickness is much greater then she thinks it is.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:103329:17"/>
            <p>Lastly, should it so fall out, that her Enemies should pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate into some of her Provinces, and lend a helping Hand to the Male-contents, that are very numerous therein, it is absolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impossible but an absolute Overturning of the whole Fabrick must ensue. Those Hot-brain'd People, prone enough to revolt, incens'd by the violent Seizures of their Estates, and the almost Insupportable Poverty and Misery to which they are reduc'd, will embrace the first Opportunity that presents it self, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if they find themselves encouraged by Forrain Support.</p>
            <p>And now we might oppose this Condition of <hi>France</hi> to the formidable Enemies that she has drawn upon her Hands; we might reflect upon the Valour of all the Chieftains of her Enemies, and more especially upon the Experience and undaunted Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of the King of <hi>Great Brittain;</hi> we might enlarge upon the Armies both English, German and Dutch, so numerous, so well train'd, so well Disciplin'd, and encourag'd by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of the most puissant Princes of the Empire, and by the great Number of Generals and other Officers, who by their Merit and their Bravery, have always signaliz'd themselves above the reach of Common Fame; we might add to all this the vast Riches of the English and Hollanders, and the magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Generosity that enclines 'em to open their Treasures with such a noble Frankness to procure that Repose and T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anquility after which all <hi>Europe</hi> sighs; but this is a Subject for a Volume by it self, nor proper to be conjoyn'd with the Design and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of this Treatise.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>